《指环王》
史麦戈！
Smeagol!
我钓到了
I've got one!
我钓到一条鱼了，史麦戈
I've got a fish, Smeag. Smeagol!
快钓上来，快呀，加油
Pull it in. Go on. Go on. Go on. Pull it in.
德戈！
Deagol!
德戈？
Deagol?
德戈
Deagol.
好兄弟，把那玩意给我
Give us that, Deagol, my love.
为什么？
Why?
因为…
Because...
今天是我生日，我要它
it's my birthday and I wants it.
我的宝贝
My precious.
他们咒骂我们
They cursed us.
杀人凶手
Murderer.
还说我们是杀人凶手
"Murderer" they called us.
他们诅咒我们，然后把我们赶走
They cursed us and drove us away.
咕鲁
Gollum.
我们哭得好惨，宝贝
And we wept, precious.
我们好孤单，哭得好惨
We wept to be so alone.
湖水好清凉，脚底板好舒服
...and cool. So nice for feet.
我们只想抓到一条大鱼
And we only wish To catch a fish.
池塘的鱼儿好甘甜
So juicy sweet.
我们忘记面包的滋味
And we forgot the taste of bread...
树木的声音
the sound of trees...
和轻柔的微风
the softness of the wind.
甚至忘记自己的名字
We even forgot our own name.
我的宝贝
My precious.
快醒醒
Wake up!
醒醒
爱睡虫，醒醒
Wake up, sleepies.
我们得走了
We must go, yes.
我们得马上出发
We must go at once.
佛罗多，你都没睡吗？
Haven't you had any sleep, Mr. Frodo?
我睡过头了
I've gone and had too much.
天色一定很晚了
Must be getting late.
没有
No.
并不晚
It isn't.
都还没过中午
It isn't midday yet.
天空越来越阴暗
The days are growing darker.
走吧
Come on!
快走吧，没时间了
Must go! No time!
佛罗多得先吃点东西再走
Not before Mr. Frodo's had something to eat.
不能浪费时间啦，笨蛋
No time to lose, silly.
拿去
Here.
那你呢？
What about you?
我不饿，反正我不爱吃兰巴斯干粮
Oh, no, I'm not hungry. Leastways, not for lembas bread.
山姆
Sam.
好吧
All right.
干粮剩不多了
We don't have that much left.
我们要省点吃，不然很快就会吃完
We have to be careful or we're going to run out.
你先吃吧，佛罗多
You go ahead and eat that, Mr. Frodo.
我算过
I've rationed it.
这趟路应该够吃
There should be enough.
哪趟路？
For what?
回家的路呀
The journey home.
来吧，小哈比人
Come, Hobbitses.
就快到了
Very close now.
就快到魔多了
Very close to Mordor.
这儿不安全
No safe places here.
快走吧
Hurry.
《国王归来》
这好棒
It's good.
绝对是来自夏尔
Definitely from the Shire.
长底烟草
Longbottom Leaf.
我觉得好像又回到绿龙旅店
I feel like I'm back at The Green Dragon.
- 绿龙旅店 - 手里拿着一杯黑啤酒
- Green Dragon. - A mug of ale in my hand.
辛苦了一整天，把脚翘起来休息
Putting my feet up on a settle after a hard day's work.
你从来就没辛苦过一整天
Only, you've never done a hard day's work.
各位大爷
Welcome, my lords...
欢迎光临艾辛格
to Isengard!
好小子，咱们拼了老命找你们
You young rascals! A merry hunt you've led us on...
你们却在这儿大吃大喝，还在抽烟斗
and now we find you feasting and... and smoking!
我们打了一场大胜仗
We are sitting on a field of victory...
当然要好好享受战果罗
enjoying a few well-earned comforts.
这块腌猪肉超好吃的
The salted pork is particularly good.
腌猪肉？
Salted pork?
- 哈比人 - 我们奉了树须的命令
- Hobbits. - We're under orders from Treebeard...
他接管了艾辛格
who's taken over management of Isengard.
年轻的甘道夫
Young Master Gandalf.
我很高兴你来了
I'm glad you've come.
我能处理树和水、岩石和货物
Wood and water, stock and stone I can master.
但是这儿有一个巫师要对付
But there is a wizard to manage here...
他被关在高塔上
locked in his tower.
现身吧
Show yourself.
小心
Be careful.
虽然萨鲁曼被击败，他还是很危险
Even in defeat, Saruman is dangerous.
把他的头砍掉不就结了
Well, let's just have his head and be done with it.
不行
No.
不能杀死他
We need him alive.
我们要问他话
We need him to talk.
你身经百战、杀敌无数，希优顿王
You have fought many wars and slain many men, Theoden King...
然后又能维持和平
and made peace afterwards.
难道我们不能像以前一样一起共商国事吗，老友？
Can we not take counsel together as we once did, my old friend?
你跟我不能和平共处吗？
Can we not have peace, you and I?
当然可以
We shall have peace.
我们可以和平共处
We shall have peace...
只要你为燃烧的西谷…
when you answer for the burning of the Westfold...
…以及死在那儿的孩童付出惨痛的代价
and the children that lie dead there!
我们可以和平共处
We shall have peace when the lives of the soldiers...
只要我们为在号角堡前壮烈牺牲的勇士…
whose bodies were hewn even as they lay dead...
…向你报仇雪恨
against the gates of the Hornburg, are avenged!
当你被吊在绞架上成为乌鸦嘴里的食物
When you hang from a gibbet for the sport of your own crows...
我们就能和平共处
we shall have peace.
绞架和乌鸦？
Gibbets and crows?
老糊涂！
Dotard!
你到底要什么，灰袍甘道夫？
What do you want, Gandalf Greyhame?
让我猜，欧散克塔的钥匙
Let me guess. The Key of Orthanc.
或者是巴拉多的钥匙
Or perhaps the Keys of Barad-dur itself...
还有七王之冠和五巫之杖
along with the crowns of the seven kings and the rods of the Five Wizards!
你的阴谋已经害死无数人命
Your treachery has already cost many lives.
成千上万人正面临危险
Thousands more are now at risk.
但是你可以救他们，萨鲁曼
But you could save them, Saruman.
你曾是敌人的心腹
You were deep in the enemy's counsel.
你是来打探军情的
So you have come here for information.
我倒是可以透露一些消急
I have some for you.
中土世界有另一股力量在蕴酿
Something festers in the heart of Middle-earth.
你并没有看到
Something that you have failed to see.
但是邪眼却看到了
But the Great Eye has seen it.
现在他会掌握这个优势
Even now he presses his advantage.
很快就会发动进攻
His attack will come soon.
你们全都会死
You're all going to die.
但是你早就知道了，对吧，甘道夫？
But you know this, don't you, Gandalf?
你不会以为这个游侠会真的坐上刚铎王位吧？
You cannot think that this Ranger will ever sit upon the throne of Gondor.
这个从阴影中爬出来的流亡者将永远不会成为人皇
This exile, crept from the shadows, will never be crowned king.
甘道夫会毫不迟疑牺牲他最亲近的朋友
Gandalf does not hesitate to sacrifice those closest to him...
那些他声称热爱的朋友
those he professes to love.
告诉我，你让那个半身人去送死之前
Tell me, what words of comfort did you give the Halfling...
跟他说了什么好话？
before you sent him to his doom?
你让他走上一条必死无疑的不归路
The path that you have set him on can only lead to death.
我听够了
I've heard enough!
杀了他，一箭把他射死吧
Shoot him. Stick an arrow in his gob.
不行
No.
萨鲁曼，只要你下来
Come down, Saruman...
- 我就饶你一命 - 你不用可怜或同情我
- and your life will be spared. - Save your pity and your mercy.
我不需要
I have no use for it!
萨鲁曼
Saruman...
你的手杖将被折断
your staff is broken.
葛力马，你不必跟随他
Grima, you need not follow him.
你以前没像现在这么坏
You were not always as you are now.
你曾经也是洛汗子弟
You were once a Man of Rohan.
下来吧
Come down.
洛汗子弟？
A Man of Rohan?
洛汗子弟算什么东西？
What is the house of Rohan...
他们不过是一群土匪住在茅草屋喝着肮脏的水
but a thatched barn where brigands drink in the reek...
他们的小孩跟畜生在地上爬来爬去
and their brats roll on the floor with the dogs?
圣盔谷的胜利不属于你骠骑国国王希优顿
The victory at Helm's Deep does not belong to you, Theoden Horse-master.
你愧对你的祖先
You are a lesser son of greater sires.
葛力马
Grima...
下来吧
come down.
摆脱他，重获自由
Be free of him.
- 自由？他永远不会自由 - 不
- Free? He will never be free. - No.
跟我走
Get down, cur!
萨鲁曼
Saruman!
你曾是敌人的心腹
You were deep in the enemy's counsel.
告诉我们你知道什么
Tell us what you know!
把你的护卫撤走，我就跟你说你会在哪里死
You withdraw your guard, and I will tell you where your doom will be decided.
我才不要被关在这里
I will not be held prisoner here.
把消息传给我们的盟友
Send word to all our allies...
以及中土世界每个自由的角落
and to every corner of Middle-earth that still stands free.
敌人准备向我们进攻，我们要知道他的目标是哪里
The enemy moves against us. We need to know where he will strike.
萨鲁曼的污秽
The filth of Saruman...
被冲得一干二净
is washing away.
树木将回来住在这儿
Trees will come back to live here.
年轻的树木
Young trees.
- 狂野的树木 - 皮聘
- Wild trees. - Pippin!
我的老天
Bless my bark!
皮端格林图克
Peregrin Took!
拿给我，小子
I'll take that, my lad.
快点交给我
Quickly, now.
今晚让我们纪念为祖国壮烈牺牲的勇士
Tonight we remember those who gave their blood to defend this country.
为死去的同胞干杯
Hail the victorious dead.
干杯
Hail!
一口气喝下去
No pauses.
- 不准洒出来 - 也不准吐出来
- No spills. - And no regurgitation.
我们在比酒量吗？
So it's a drinking game?
最后一个站着不倒的人赢
Last one standing wins.
为胜利干杯
What'll we drink to? Let's drink to victory!
胜利
To victory!
我为你感到高兴
I am happy for you.
他是个男子汉
He is an honorable man.
你们都是男子汉
You are both honorable men.
率领洛汗人打胜仗的并不是我希优顿王
It was not Theoden of Rohan who led our people to victory.
你不必听我发牢骚
Don't listen to me.
你还年轻
You are young.
今晚属于你
And tonight is for you.
干杯
Here, here.
矮人要跟全身长毛的矮小女人一起游泳
It's the Dwarves that go swimming with little, hairy women.
我觉得怪怪的
I feel something.
我的手有点麻
A slight tingle in my fingers.
我想我喝醉了
I think it's affecting me.
我就说吧
What did I say?
他的酒量很差
He can't hold his liquor.
他玩完了
Game over.
你可以在远方寻觅或是把酒喝到见底
Oh, you can search far and wide You can drink the whole town dry
但是你却找不到
But you'll never find a beer so brown But you'll never find a beer so brown
比我们家乡更醇的啤酒
As the one we drink in our hometown As the one we drink in our hometown
你可以一杯接一杯狂饮上等麦酒
You can drink your fancy ales You can drink them by the flagon
但是勇士喝的美酒…
But the only brew for the brave and true
皮聘
Pippin!
但是勇士喝的美酒
But the only brew for the brave and true
只有绿龙旅店才有
Comes from The Green Dragon
谢谢大家，我赢了
Thank you! I win!
没有佛罗多的消息？
No news of Frodo?
一点消息也没有
No word. Nothing.
还有时间
We have time.
佛罗多越来越接近魔多了
Every day, Frodo moves closer to Mordor.
我们能确定吗？
Do we know that?
你有什么直觉？
What does your heart tell you?
佛罗多还活着
That Frodo is alive.
没错
Yes.
他还活着
Yes, he's alive.
太冒险了，太冒险了
Too risky. Too risky.
这些小偷
Thieves.
他们从我们手上偷走它
They stole it from us.
杀死他们，把他们两个都杀死
Kill them. Kill them. Kill them both.
安静，不能吵醒他们
Quiet! Mustn't wake them.
不然就会前功尽弃
Mustn't ruin it now.
可是他们知道了
But they knows.
他们都知道了
They knows.
他们对我们起了疑心
They suspects us.
你是怎么了，好兄弟？
What's it saying, my precious, my love?
史麦戈是不是怕了？
Is Smeagol losing his nerve?
没有，我不怕
No. Not.
我才不怕呢，史麦戈痛恨臭哈比人
Never. Smeagol hates nasty Hobbitses.
史麦戈要给他们死
Smeagol wants to see them dead.
我们会杀死他们
And we will.
史麦戈杀过人，可以再下毒手
Smeagol did it once. He can do it again.
它是我们的
It's ours!
我们的
Ours!
我们一定要得到宝贝，一定要把它抢回来
We must get the precious. We must get it back.
耐心点，你要有点耐心
Patience! Patience, my love.
我们要先把他们带到她那儿
First we must lead them to her.
带他们走上弯曲阶梯
We lead them to the Winding Stair.
没错，然后呢？
Yes, the stairs. And then?
一直往上爬、往上爬
Up, up, up, up, up the stairs we go...
直到我们来到…那条隧道
until we come to the tunnel.
他们一进去
And when they go in...
就永远出不来
there's no coming out.
她一直都肚子饿
She's always hungry.
她要填饱肚子
She always needs to feed.
就一定要吃肉
She must eat.
她只吃得到臭半兽人
All she gets is filthy Orcses.
味道又臭又难吃，对吧，宝贝？
And they doesn't taste very nice, does they, precious?
对
No.
一点也不好吃
Not very nice at all, my love.
她一直想吃更甜美的肉
She hungers for sweeter meats.
哈比人的肉
Hobbit meat.
等她吃饱了，把骨头和衣服都吐出来
And when she throws away the bones and the empty clothes...
我们就会找到它
then we will find it.
然后我要把它拿走
And take it for me!
是我们
For us.
对，我是说我们
Yes. We meant "for us."
咕鲁、咕鲁
Gollum. Gollum.
只要小哈比人一死
The precious will be ours...
宝贝就属于我们
once the Hobbitses are dead!
你这可恶的小坏蛋
You treacherous little toad!
不！主人！
No! No! Master!
住手，山姆，别打他
No, Sam! Leave him alone!
我亲耳听见他说要杀死我们
I heard it from his own mouth. He means to murder us.
没有，史麦戈连苍蝇都不敢杀
Never! Smeagol wouldn't hurt a fly.
他是个又胖又丑的哈比人
He's a horrid, fat Hobbit...
他讨厌史麦戈
who hates Smeagol...
所以才乱编谎话
and who makes up nasty lies.
你这小坏蛋，我要把你搂扁
You miserable little maggot! I'll stove your head in!
山姆
Sam!
你敢说我骗人？你才在当面撒谎
Call me a liar? You're a liar!
- 你把他吓跑我们就会迷路 - 我不管，我办不到
- You scare him off, we're lost! - I don't care! I can't do it, Mr. Frodo.
- 我不能坐着让他杀死我们 - 我不会把他赶走
- I won't wait around for him to kill us! - I'm not sending him away.
你看不出来吗？
You don't see it, do you?
他是个坏蛋
He's a villain.
我们光靠自己不行，没有人带路就到不了
We can't do this by ourselves, Sam. Not without a guide.
我需要你在我身边
I need you on my side.
我一直在你身边，佛罗多
I'm on your side, Mr. Frodo.
我知道，山姆，我知道
I know, Sam. I know.
你要相信我
Trust me.
来吧，史麦戈
Come, Smeagol.
现在是什么时辰？
What time is it?
还没有破晓
Not yet dawn.
我梦到我看见一道巨浪
I dreamed I saw a great wave...
淹没了绿色平原，大水一直冲到山坡
climbing over green lands and above the hills.
我站在大水边缘
I stood upon the brink.
脚底下是一片漆黑的无底洞
It was utterly dark in the abyss before my feet.
我身后有一道亮光
A light shone behind me...
但是我却无法回头
but I could not turn.
我只能站在那儿，等待着
I could only stand there, waiting.
人到了晚上就会胡思乱想
Night changes many thoughts.
睡吧，伊欧玟
Sleep, Eowyn.
趁你还能睡
Sleep...
快睡吧
while you can.
星光被阴影遮住
The stars are veiled.
东方有什么在蠢蠢欲动
Something stirs in the east.
一股永不歇息的邪恶力量
A sleepless malice.
敌人的邪眼在移动
The Eye of the enemy is moving.
你在干嘛？
What are you doing?
皮聘
Pippin!
皮聘？
Pippin?
皮聘
Pippin.
- 你发疯了吗？ - 我只想看一眼
- What, are you mad? - I just want to look at it.
我只想再看一眼
Just one more time.
放回去
Put it back.
皮聘
Pippin.
不
No!
皮聘
Pippin.
他在这儿
He is here.
我看到你了
I see you.
皮聘
Pippin!
救命啊，甘道夫
Help! Gandalf, help!
快救救他
Someone help him!
皮聘
Pippin!
你这个蠢小子
Fool of a Took!
看着我
Look at me.
甘道夫，原谅我
Gandalf, forgive me.
看着我
Look at me.
你看到什么？
What did you see?
一棵树
A tree.
有一棵白树
There was a white tree...
在石砌的庭院中央
in a courtyard of stone.
它枯死了
It was dead.
城市在燃烧
The city was burning.
米那斯提力斯，你只看到这些？
Minas Tirith? Is that what you saw?
我还看到…
I saw...
我看到他
I saw him.
我听到他的声音
I could hear his voice in my head.
你跟他说了什么？
And what did you tell him?
快说
Speak!
他问我是谁，我没回答
He asked me my name. I didn't answer.
他伤害了我
He hurt me.
你有没有提到佛罗多和魔戒？
What did you tell him about Frodo and the Ring?
我看得出皮聘没说谎
There was no lie in Pippin's eyes.
他是个蠢小子
A fool...
不过是个诚实的蠢小子
but an honest fool he remains.
他没跟索伦提到佛罗多和魔戒的事
He told Sauron nothing of Frodo and the Ring.
我们算是很幸运
We've been strangely fortunate.
皮聘在真知晶球上看到敌人的计划
Pippin saw in the palantir a glimpse of the enemy's plan.
索伦打算攻击米那斯提力斯
Sauron moves to strike the city of Minas Tirith.
他在圣盔谷的惨败让他知道一件事
His defeat at Helm's Deep showed our enemy one thing.
伊兰迪尔的继承人出现了
He knows the heir of Elendil has come forth.
人类并没有他想的那么脆弱
Men are not as weak as he supposed.
人类仍有勇气，也许有足够力量挑战他
There is courage still, strength enough perhaps to challenge him.
索伦害怕这一点
Sauron fears this.
他不能让中土世界的人民在同一个旗帜下奋勇作战
He will not risk the peoples of Middle-earth uniting under one banner.
他打算摧毁米那斯提力斯
He will raze Minas Tirith to the ground...
阻止人类的王者再临
before he sees a king return to the throne of Men.
如果刚铎点燃烽火，洛汗国必须准备参战
If the beacons of Gondor are lit, Rohan must be ready for war.
告诉我
Tell me...
他们没来帮助我们，凭什么要我们出兵救援？
why should we ride to the aid of those who did not come to ours?
我们欠刚铎什么吗？
What do we owe Gondor?
- 我去好了 - 不行
- I will go. - No!
- 一定要警告他们 - 他们会受到警告
- They must be warned. - They will be.
你要从另一条路去那儿
You must come to Minas Tirith by another road.
溯河而上，寻找黑色大船
Follow the river. Look to the black ships.
你们要明白
Understand this:
大战有如箭在弦上一触即发
Things are now in motion that cannot be undone.
我要去米那斯提力斯
I ride for Minas Tirith...
但我不会一个人去
and I won't be going alone.
皮端格林图克，你这个爱管闲事的哈比人
Of all the inquisitive Hobbits, Peregrin Took, you are the worst.
快！快！
Hurry! Hurry!
我们要去哪儿？
Where are we going?
你为什么要乱看咧？
Why did you look?
你为什么每次都要乱看？
Why do you always have to look?
- 晓得，我忍不住 - 你每次都忍不住
- I don't know. I can't help it. - You never can.
对不起啦
I'm sorry, all right?
- 我下次不敢了 - 你还不懂吗？
- I won't do it again. - Don't you understand?
魔王以为魔戒在你手上
The enemy thinks you have the Ring.
他会来找你，皮聘，他们一定要把你带走
He's going to be looking for you, Pip. They have to get you out of here.
你呢？你会跟我来吧？
And you? You're coming with me?
梅里？
Merry?
走吧
Come on.
米那斯提力斯有多远？
How far is Minas Tirith?
骑马要骑三天，戒灵都用飞的
Three days' ride, as the Nazgul flies.
你最好祈祷他们不会追上来
And you better hope we don't have one of those on our tail.
拿去
Here.
给你在路上抽
Something for the road.
最后一包长底烟草
The last of the Longbottom Leaf.
我知道你抽完了，你抽得太凶了
I know you've run out. You smoke too much, Pippin.
可是，我们很快会再见面
But... But we'll see each other soon.
- 对吧？ - 我不知道
- Won't we? - I don't know.
我不知道以后的事
I don't know what's going to happen.
- 梅里 - 快跑，影疾
- Merry. - Run, Shadowfax.
用最快的速度狂奔
Show us the meaning of haste.
梅里！
Merry!
从小时候开始
He's always followed me...
不管我去哪里
everywhere I went...
他都黏着我不放
since before we were tweens.
我总是害他惹上各种麻烦
I would get him into the worst sort of trouble...
可是我也一定会替他解围
but I was always there to get him out.
现在他不在了
Now he's gone.
就跟佛罗多和山姆一样
Just like Frodo and Sam.
我从哈比人身上学到一件事
One thing I have learned about Hobbits:
他们都很坚强
They're a most hardy folk.
有时候也很傻，他是图克家子弟
Foolhardy, maybe. He's a Took.
带她走最安全的路
Take her by the safest road.
有一艘船停靠在灰港岸
A ship lies anchored in the Grey Havens.
等着载她到海外仙境
It waits to carry her across the sea.
这是亚玟安多米尔的最后之旅
The last journey of Arwen Undomiel.
你留下来什么也没有
There is nothing for you here...
只有死亡
only death.
亚玟公主
Lady Arwen...
不能再耽误时间了
we cannot delay.
公主
My lady!
- 告诉我你看到什么？ - 亚玟
- Tell me what you have seen. - Arwen.
你有预知的能力
You have the gift of foresight.
你看见什么？
What did you see?
我看见你的未来有死亡
I looked into your future, and I saw death.
但是也有新生
But there is also life.
有一个小孩，那是我的儿子
You saw there was a child. You saw my son.
这个未来可能无法成真
That future is almost gone.
但是仍有希望
But it is not lost.
你不能确定
Nothing is certain.
我只确定一件事
Some things are certain.
如果我现在离开他
If I leave him now...
一定会终生悔恨
I will regret it forever.
是时候了
It is time.
火花将从死灰中复燃
From the ashes a fire shall be woken
光明将从阴影中再现
A light from the shadow shall spring
断裂的圣剑将重新接上
Renewed shall be blade that was broken
失去王冠者将成为人皇
The crownless again shall be king
请你重铸圣剑
Re-forge the sword.
你的手好冰冷
Your hands are cold.
你已失去精灵的永生
The life of the Eldar is leaving you.
这是我的选择
This was my choice.
不管你答不答应
Whether by your will or not...
我都不会搭船离开这儿
there is no ship now that can bear me hence.
我们刚刚越过刚铎边界
We've just passed into the realm of Gondor.
米那斯提力斯
Minas Tirith.
众王之城
City of kings.
让开
Make way!
就是那棵树
It's the tree.
甘道夫、甘道夫
Gandalf. Gandalf.
这就是刚铎的圣白树
Yes, the White Tree of Gondor.
王者之树
The tree of the king.
但是迪耐瑟并不是国王
Lord Denethor, however, is not king.
他只是刚铎的宰相和摄政王
He is a steward only, a caretaker of the throne.
给我听好了，迪耐瑟大人是波罗莫的父亲
Now listen carefully. Lord Denethor is Boromir's father.
你最好别让他知道他爱子的死讯
To give him news of his beloved son's death would be most unwise.
也别提起佛罗多和魔戒的事
And do not mention Frodo or the Ring.
更别提到亚拉冈
And say nothing of Aragorn either.
你最好一句话都不要说，皮端格林图克
In fact, it's better if you don't speak at all, Peregrin Took.
迪耐瑟大人，爱克西里昂之子，刚铎的宰相和摄政王
Hail Denethor, son of Ecthelion, lord and steward of Gondor.
我在黑暗的时刻前来提供我的忠告
I come with tidings in this dark hour, and with counsel.
也许你能给我一个交代
Perhaps you come to explain this.
也许你是来告诉我我儿子的死因
Perhaps you come to tell me why my son is dead.
波罗莫是为了救我们而死
Boromir died to save us...
我跟我的同胞
my kinsman and me.
- 他为了保护我们壮烈牺牲 - 皮聘
- He fell defending us from many foes. - Pippin.
为了回报他的救命之恩
I offer you my service, such as it is...
我愿意效忠于你
in payment of this debt.
既然如此我要问你
This is my first command to you.
你为什么能逃走，而我儿子武艺这么高强
How did you escape and my son did not...
却不能活着逃出来？
so mighty a man as he was?
强者只要中一箭就会死
The mightiest man may be slain by one arrow...
况且波罗莫身中了好几箭
and Boromir was pierced by many.
起来
Get up.
大人，请你以后再为波罗莫哀悼
My lord, there will be a time to grieve for Boromir...
现在并不是时候
but it is not now.
大战即将展开
War is coming.
敌军已经逼近边界，你身为刚铎宰相
The enemy is on your doorstep. As steward, you are charged...
必须捍卫这座城市，刚铎的大军在哪里？
with the defense of this city. Where are Gondor's armies?
你仍然有盟友，并不会孤军奋战
You still have friends. You are not alone in this fight.
向洛汗国的希优顿王求救，点燃烽火
Send word to Theoden of Rohan. Light the beacons.
你自以为很聪明，米斯兰达
You think you are wise, Mithrandir.
但是你却低估了我
Yet for all your subtleties, you have not wisdom.
你以为我是瞎了眼睛吗？
Do you think the eyes of the White Tower are blind?
我知道的比你想像的多
I have seen more than you know.
你一方面想利用我对抗魔多
With your left hand you would use me as a shield against Mordor.
另一方面想趁机推翻我
And with your right you'd seek to supplant me.
我知道谁在协助希优顿王
I know who rides with Theoden of Rohan.
没错，我早就听过亚拉冈了，他是亚拉松之子
Oh, yes. Word has reached my ears of this Aragorn, son of Arathorn.
我要告诉你，我才不会向北方游侠屈服
And I tell you now, I will not bow to this Ranger from the North...
他只是失去王位的落魄王族
last of a ragged house long bereft of lordship.
你没有权利拒绝人皇回归，宰相大人
Authority is not given to you to deny the return of the king, steward.
除了我没有人能统治刚铎
The rule of Gondor is mine and no other's.
来吧
Come.
他现在眼里只有权力
All has turned to vain ambition.
他甚至会用哀伤掩饰他的野心
He would even use his grief as a cloak.
这座王都屹立了一千年
A thousand years this city has stood.
现在它将毁于一个疯子的手中
Now, at the whim of a madman, it will fall.
而圣白树，王者之树
And the White Tree, the tree of the king...
将永远不会开花
will never bloom again.
他们为什么还在守着它？
Why are they still guarding it?
因为他们仍抱有一线希望
They guard it because they have hope.
这个小小的希望有一天会开花结果
A faint and fading hope that one day it will flower.
人皇将回归，王都也将恢复昔日光辉
That a king will come and this city will be as it once was...
不会遭到毁灭
before it fell into decay.
西方孕育的智慧早被遗忘
The old wisdom borne out of the West was forsaken.
历任国王盖的墓陵远比王宫还要奢华
Kings made tombs more splendid than the houses of the living...
他们只会缅怀先祖的丰功伟业
and counted the old names of their descent...
却对自己的儿子不屑一顾
dearer than the names of their sons.
后继无人的城主坐在古老的宫殿墨守成规
Childless lords sat in aged halls, musing on heraldry...
或是登上冰冷的高塔求神问运、占星卜卦
or in high, cold towers, asking questions of the stars.
因此刚铎人民命运堪虞
And so the people of Gondor fell into ruin.
王室香火无以为继
The line of kings failed.
圣白树也枯萎凋零
The White Tree withered.
刚铎将落入敌人手中
The rule of Gondor was given over to lesser men.
魔多
Mordor.
是的，它就在那儿
Yes, there it lies.
这座城市长久以来都笼罩在它的阴影之下
This city has dwelt ever in the sight of its shadow.
暴风雨即将来临
A storm is coming.
这并不是自然的现象
This is not the weather of the world.
而是索伦一手造成的异象
This is a device of Sauron's making.
这也是他大举进攻的前兆
A broil of fume he sends ahead of his host.
魔多的半兽人不能忍受阳光
The Orcs of Mordor have no love of daylight...
所以他就将太阳遮蔽
so he covers the face of the sun...
好让他们踏上征途
to ease their passage along the road to war.
当魔多的魔影到达这座城市
When the Shadow of Mordor reaches this city...
大战就会展开
it will begin.
是哦
Well...
米那斯提力斯
Minas Tirith...
真是令人叹为观止
very impressive.
- 我们还要去哪儿？ - 现在要走太迟了，皮聘
- So where are we off to next? - Oh, it's too late for that, Peregrin.
我们无法离开这座城市
There's no leaving this city.
救兵一定要赶来支援
Help must come to us.
下午茶时间一定快到了
It must be getting near teatime.
如果在好一点的地方，就一定会有下午茶时间
Leastways, it would be in decent places where there is still teatime.
我们不是在一个好地方
We're not in decent places.
佛罗多？
Mr. Frodo?
怎么了？
What is it?
我有一种预感
It's just a feeling.
我想我回不了家了
I don't think I'll be coming back.
你回得了家，你一定会回家
Yes, you will. Of course you will.
你别瞎想了
That's just morbid thinking.
我们一定会去而复返
We're going there and back again...
就跟比尔博一样
just like Mr. Bilbo.
你等着瞧
You'll see.
这些土地曾经是刚铎王国的一部份
I think these lands were once part of the kingdom of Gondor.
在很久以前，还有国王的时候
Long ago, when there was a king.
佛罗多，你看
Mr. Frodo, look.
国王头上又有王冠了
The king has got a crown again.
快来啊，哈比人，不要停下来，往这儿走
Come on, Hobbits! Mustn't stop now. This way.
我猜我只是挂名的卫兵吧
So I imagine this is just a ceremonial position.
我是说我不必真的上战场吧
I mean, they don't actually expect me to do any fighting.
- 对不对？ - 你已经对宰相宣誓效忠
- Do they? - You're in the service of the steward now.
你必须奉命行事，皮端格林图克
You'll have to do as you're told, Peregrin Took.
傻哈比人
Ridiculous Hobbit.
刚铎卫兵
Guard of the Citadel.
谢谢你
Thank you.
天上没有星星
There's no more stars.
时候到了吗？
Is it time?
是的
Yes.
好安静哦
It's so quiet.
这只是暴风雨前的宁静
It's the deep breath before the plunge.
我并不想上战场
I don't want to be in a battle...
但是等待一场不可避免的大战更令人害怕
but waiting on the edge of one I can't escape is even worse.
甘道夫，佛罗多和山姆有成功的希望吗？
Is there any hope, Gandalf, for Frodo and Sam?
他们的希望并不大
There never was much hope.
只有一线希望
Just a fool's hope.
敌人已蓄势待发
Our enemy is ready.
他集结了强大兵力
His full strength's gathered.
不只是半兽人，还有人类
Not only Orcs, but Men as well.
来自南方的哈拉德林人部队
Legions of Haradrim from the south...
以及来自海岸的佣兵
mercenaries from the coast.
全都听从魔多的命令
All will answer Mordor's call.
来吧
Come on.
刚铎将难逃灭亡的命运
This will be the end of Gondor as we know it.
敌人会对这里展开猛烈攻势
Here the hammer stroke will fall hardest.
如果安都因河被占领，奥斯吉力亚斯碉堡被攻陷
If the river is taken, if the garrison at Osgiliath falls...
这座城市的最后防线就会瓦解
the last defense of this city will be gone.
还有你这个白袍巫师，你一定会有办法的
But we have the White Wizard. That's got to count for something.
对吧，甘道夫？
Gandalf?
索伦还没派出最厉害的手下
Sauron has yet to reveal his deadliest servant...
他将率领魔多大军进行攻击
the one who will lead Mordor's armies in war.
据说没有活人杀得了他
The one they say no living man can kill.
安格马的巫王
The Witch King of Angmar.
你见过他
You've met him before.
他在风云顶刺了佛罗多一剑
He stabbed Frodo on Weathertop.
他就是戒灵之王
He is the lord of the Nazgul...
九骑士之首
the greatest of the Nine.
他的巢穴是米那斯魔窟
Minas Morgul is his lair.
死城
The Dead City.
很可怕的地方，到处都是敌人
Very nasty place. Full of enemies.
快点，快呀
Quick. Quick.
他们会看到我们
They will see. They will see.
别过去，别过去，瞧，我们找到了
Come away. Come away. Look, we have found it.
通往魔多的路
The way into Mordor.
秘密阶梯
The secret stair.
往上爬
Climb.
- 不，佛罗多 - 不是那里
- No, Mr. Frodo! - Not that way!
- 在干嘛？ - 别去
- What's it doing? - No.
- 戒灵在召唤我 - 糟了
- They're calling me. - No.
快躲起来，躲起来
Hide! Hide!
我成觉得到他的剑锋
I can feel his blade.
决战时刻终于来临
We come to it at last.
魔戒圣战即将展开
The great battle of our time.
来吧，小哈比人，我们一定要爬上去
Come away, Hobbits. We climb. We must climb.
棋盘已经摆好
The board is set.
棋子闲始移动
The pieces are moving.
爬上去，爬上阶梯
Up, up, up the stairs we go.
然后就进入隧道
And then it's into the tunnel.
这个隧道里头有什么？
Hey, what's in this tunnel?
听我说，你给我听好了
You listen to me, and you listen good and proper.
要是他出事你说会倒大楣
Anything happens to him, you have me to answer to.
我只要开到什么不对劲
One sniff something's not right...
要是我背上的汗毛竖起来，你就玩完了
one hair stands up on the back of my head, it's over.
我要宰了你这臭东西，你休想有好日子过
No more slinker. No more stinker.
你死定了，懂吗？
You're gone. Got it?
我在看着你
I'm watching you.
你刚才跟他说什么？
What was that about?
没什么，只是交代一些事
Nothing. Just clearing something up.
皮聘，你要完成一项任务
Peregrin Took, my lad, there is a task now to be done.
让你这哈比人有机会再一次证明自己的能力
Another opportunity for one of the Shire-folk to prove their great worth.
你绝对不能失败
You must not fail me.
敌人在对岸没有任何动静
It's been very quiet across the river.
半兽人躲起来了
The Orcs are lying low.
他们很可能已经撤退
The garrison may have moved out.
我们派了探子到凯尔安卓斯
We've sent scouts to Cair Andros.
如果半兽人从北边进攻，我们一定会有预警
If the Orcs attack from the north, we'll have some warning.
安静
Quiet.
还需要十个人
We need 10 more.
杀了他
Kill him!
他们并不是从北边进攻
They're not coming from the north.
快赶到河边，快点
To the river. Quick. Quick. Go. Come on.
划快一点
Faster.
拔剑
Draw swords.
挡住他们
Hold! Hold them!
那是什么？
What?
阿蒙丁
Amon Din
阿蒙丁的烽火点燃了
The beacon. The beacon of Amon Din is lit.
终于燃起一线希望
Hope is kindled.
米那斯提力斯的烽火，烽火点燃了
The beacons of Minas Tirith! The beacons are lit!
刚铎向我们求救
Gondor calls for aid.
洛汗国将前往支援
And Rohan will answer.
洛汗国全军集结
Muster the Rohirrim.
召集登哈洛大军
Assemble the army at Dunharrow.
尽量召集人马，我给你两天时间
As many men as can be found. You have two days.
第三天就整装出发，前往刚铎展开大战
On the third, we ride for Gondor and war.
- 前进 - 很好
- Forward. - Very good, sir.
- 加姆林 - 王上
- Gamling. - My lord.
全速跨越洛汗平原
Make haste across the Riddermark.
召集人马前往登哈洛
Summon every able-bodied man to Dunharrow.
遵命
I will.
- 你跟我们一起去吗？ - 我最远只能跟到营地
- Will you ride with us? - Just to the encampment.
按照传统，王女必须为士兵送行
It's tradition for the women of the court to farewell the men.
人民找到他们的领袖
The men have found their captain.
他们愿意跟随你作战，甚至愿意壮烈牺牲
They will follow you into battle, even to death.
你给了我们希望
You have given us hope.
对不起
Excuse me.
我有一把剑
I have a sword.
请你让我参战
Please accept it.
我愿意为你效忠，希优顿王
I offer you my service, Theoden King.
我很乐意接受
And gladly I accept it.
我封你为洛汗骑士梅里雅达克
You shall be Meriadoc, esquire of Rohan.
骠骑勇士
Horse-Men.
我真希望能召集矮人大军，披上盔甲和你们并肩作战
I wish I could muster a legion of Dwarves, fully armed and filthy.
你的族人不需要参战
Your kinsmen may have no need to ride to war.
战争就已经找上门了
I fear war already marches on their own lands.
米那斯提力斯的攻城战
So it is before the walls of Minas Tirith...
将决定人类是否将会灭亡
the doom of our time will be decided.
这是决战时刻，洛汗骑士，你们曾誓死奋战
Now is the hour. Riders of Rohan, oaths you have taken.
现在该行动了，为吾王及国土作战
Now, fulfill them all. To lord and land!
法拉墨
Faramir!
我们抵挡不了，城市已经沦陷
We can't hold them. The city is lost.
下令撤退，我们退回米那斯提力斯
Tell the men to break cover. We ride for Minas Tirith.
戒灵
Nazgul.
快找掩护
Take cover!
戒灵
Nazgul!
彻退，退回米那斯提力斯
Fall back. Fall back to Minas Tirith!
快撤退
Fall back!
- 撤退！撤退！ - 快逃命吧
- Retreat! Retreat! - Run for your lives!
人类的时代结束了
The age of Men is over.
半兽人的时代来临了
The time of the Orc has come.
- 向前跑 - 是戒灵
- Keep going. - It's the Nazgul.
大人，快找掩护
Take cover, my lord!
他们来了
It's coming!
- 是米斯兰达 - 白袍骑士
- It's Mithrandir. - The White Rider!
打开城门
Pull!
米斯兰达
Mithrandir.
他们攻破我们的防线
They broke through our defenses.
占领了桥梁和西岸
They've taken the bridge and the west bank.
- 兽人大军正越河而来 - 迪耐瑟大人早就料到了
- Battalions of Orcs are crossing the river. - It is as the Lord Denethor predicted.
- 他早就预知有这种结局 - 他却什么也不做
- Long has he foreseen this doom. - Foreseen and done nothing.
法拉墨？
Faramir?
这不是你第一次见到半身人
This is not the first Halfling to have crossed your path.
没错
No.
你见到佛罗多和山姆？
You've seen Frodo and Sam?
- 在哪里？几时？ - 在伊西力安
- Where? When? - In Ithilien.
不到两天前
Not two days ago.
他们往魔窟谷的方向前进
Gandalf, they're taking the road to the Morgul Vale.
然后会通过西力斯昂哥隘口
And then the pass of Cirith Ungol.
这是什么意思？
What does that mean?
- 怎么了？ - 法拉墨，把一切经过告诉我
- What's wrong? - Faramir, tell me everything.
把你知道的都告诉我
Tell me all you know.
你就是这样效忠王都吗？
This is how you would serve your city?
你要让它遭到毁灭？
You would risk its utter ruin?
我以我的判断做出正确决定
I did what I judged to be right.
你判断的正确决定？
What you judged to be right.
你把手持权力之戒的半身人送进魔多的魔掌
You sent the Ring of Power into Mordor in the hands of a witless Halfling.
你应该把魔戒带回来，放在安全的地方
It should have been brought back to the Citadel to be kept safe.
藏起来
Hidden.
锁在严密的保险库里
Dark and deep in the vaults...
绝对不能使用
not to be used.
除非在最危急的时刻
Unless at the uttermost end of need.
我绝不会使用魔戒
I would not use the Ring.
就算米那斯提力斯沦陷，只剩下我一人能捍卫它
Not if Minas Tirith were falling in ruin and I alone could save her.
你一直想效法古代的国王
Ever you desire to appear lordly and gracious...
像他们一样大公无私
as a king of old.
波罗莫就会记得他父亲的需求
Boromir would have remembered his father's need.
他就会把那个贵重的礼物带来给我
He would have brought me a kingly gift.
波罗莫才不会把魔戒带来
Boromir would not have brought the Ring.
他会伸出手抢走魔戒，沦为魔王的爪牙
He would have stretched out his hand to this thing and taken it. He would've fallen.
- 你什么也不懂 - 他会把魔戒占为己有
- You know nothing of this matter! - He would have kept it for his own.
然后当他回来
And when he returned...
你绝对认不出自己的儿子
you would not have known your son.
波罗莫对我忠心耿耿
Boromir was loyal to me!
他不是巫师的徒弟
Not some wizard's pupil!
父亲
Father?
儿子
My son.
你走吧
Leave me.
小心点，主人，小心点
Careful, master. Careful.
这座山谷很深
Very far to fall.
这些阶梯很危险
Very dangerous are the stairs.
来吧，主人
Come, master.
到史麦戈这儿
Come to Smeagol.
佛罗多
Mr. Frodo.
你给我退后
Get back, you!
别碰他
Don't touch him!
他为什么这么痛恨可怜的史麦戈？
Why does he hates poor Smeagol?
史麦戈到底对他做了什么？
What has Smeagol ever done to him?
主人？
Master?
主人身上的担子好沉重
Master carries heavy burden.
史麦戈知道，好沉重的担子
Smeagol knows. Heavy, heavy burden.
小胖子不会懂
Fat one cannot know.
史麦戈会照顾主人
Smeagol look after master.
他想要它
He wants it.
他需要它，我从他的眼神看得出来
He needs it. Smeagol sees it in his eye.
他很快就会向你要，你等着瞧
Very soon he will ask you for it. You will see.
小胖子会把它从你手中抢过去
The fat one will take it from you.
派出所有军队
Send forth all legions.
全力进攻直到把城市攻陷
Do not stop the attack until the city is taken.
把他们赶尽杀绝
Slay them all.
- 巫师呢？ - 我会对付他
- What of the wizard? - I will break him.
希优顿王的骠骑呢？
Where are Theoden's riders?
洛汗大军会来吗？
Will Rohan's army come?
米斯兰达
Mithrandir.
你们最犀利的武器就是勇气
Courage is the best defense that you have now.
你到底在想什么，皮端格林图克？
What were you thinking, Peregrin Took?
像我这个小哈比人能为伟大的城主做什么？
What service can a Hobbit offer such a great lord of Men?
你已经做得很好了
It was well-done.
你这种慷慨激昂的行为不该受到冰冷的劝阻
A generous deed should not be checked with cold counsel.
你要加入要塞卫戍部队
You are to join the tower guard.
我还以为他们找不到我适合穿的军服
I didn't think they would find any livery that would fit me.
这身军服曾经属于一个少年
Once belonged to a young boy of the city.
一个很愚蠢的少年
A very foolish one...
他浪费太多时间屠龙，没有乖乖学习
who wasted many hours slaying dragons instead of attending to his studies.
- 这是你的吗？ - 是的
- This was yours? - Yes, it was mine.
这是我父亲替我缝制的
My father had it made for me.
可是
Well...
我比你当时还要高
I'm taller than you were then.
不过我不会再长高了，只会长胖
Though I'm not likely to grow anymore, except sideways.
我穿军服也不太适合
Never fitted me either.
波罗莫比较像一个军人
Boromir was always the soldier.
他跟我父亲其实很像
They were so alike, he and my father.
心高气傲
Proud.
他们都很固执
Stubborn even.
但是却很坚强
But strong.
你拥有不同的力量
I think you have strength of a different kind.
有一天你父亲会了解
And one day your father will see it.
我在此宣誓效忠刚铎
Here do I swear fealty and service to Gondor...
不管和平或战争
in peace or war...
置生死于度外
in living or dying...
从…
from...
从现在开始
From this hour henceforth...
直到大人解除我的誓言
until my lord release me...
或是直到我死为止
or death take me.
我不会忘记你的誓言
And I shall not forget it...
也一定会回应你的效忠
nor fail to reward that which is given.
以爱回应忠诚
Fealty with love.
以荣誉回应英勇
Valor with honor.
以后仇回应背叛
Disloyalty with vengeance.
你不该轻易放弃边界防线
I do not think we should so lightly abandon the outer defenses...
那是你兄长一直坚守的防线
defenses that your brother long held intact.
- 你要我怎么做？ - 我们不能说这样弃守…
- What would you have me do? - I will not yield...
帕兰诺平原和安都因河
the river in Pelennor unfought.
一定要夺回奥斯吉力亚斯
Osgiliath must be retaken.
奥斯吉力亚斯已经被攻陷
My lord, Osgiliath is overrun.
打仗一定有风险
Much must be risked in war.
有哪位将军有勇气为摄政王效命？
Is there a captain here who still has the courage to do his lord's will?
你希望我跟哥哥交换命运
You wish now that our places had been exchanged...
你宁愿我死，让波罗莫活
that I had died and Boromir had lived.
是的
Yes.
我是这么希望
I wish that.
既然你失去了波罗莫
Since you were robbed of Boromir...
我就代替他执行这项任务
I will do what I can in his stead.
如果我能生还，请你肯定我的能力
If I should return, think better of me, Father.
这要看你是不是能凯旋归来
That will depend on the manner of your return.
你想干什么？
What are you up to?
你想偷溜，对吧？
Sneaking off, are we?
偷溜？
Sneaking?
小胖子真有良心
Fat Hobbit is always so polite.
史麦戈带他们找到没有人找得到的秘密通道
Smeagol shows them secret ways that nobody else could find...
他却说我想偷溜
and they say "sneak."
偷溜？
Sneak?
你真是个好朋友，是啊，你真是个好兄弟
Very nice friend. Oh, yes, my precious.
- 好兄弟 - 够了，够了
- Very nice, very nice. - All right. All right!
我只是被你吓了一跳
You just startled me is all.
你冈J才在干嘛？
What were you doing?
偷溜呀
Sneaking.
好吧，随便你
Fine. Have it your own way.
很抱歉把你吵醒
I'm sorry to wake you, Mr. Frodo.
我们得出发了
We have to be moving on.
天色还是很暗
It's dark still.
天色一直都很暗
It's always dark here.
不见了
It's gone!
- 精灵干粮不见了 - 什么？
- The Elven bread. - What?
我们只剩下那点干粮
That's all we have left.
他拿走了，一定是他偷的
He took it. He must have!
你说我？可怜的史麦戈才没拿
Smeagol? No, no, not poor Smeagol.
史麦戈最讨厌吃精灵干粮
Smeagol hates nasty Elf bread.
你骗人，你拿到哪儿了？
You're a lying rat! What did you do with it?!
他不吃那玩意
He doesn't eat it.
- 不可能是他拿的 - 瞧
- He can't have taken it. - Look.
这是什么？
What's this?
他的外套上有干粮屑，是他拿的
Crumbs on his jacketses. He took it!
是他偷走的
He took it.
我亲眼看到他老是趁主人不注意偷吃
I seen him. He's always stuffing his face when master's not looking.
你说谎
That's a filthy lie!
你这个狡猾的小坏蛋
You stinking, two-faced sneak!
- 山姆 - 你敢说是我
- Sam! - Call me...
住手
Stop it!
山姆
Sam!
- 我要宰了他 - 山姆，不！
- I'll kill him! - Sam! No!
对不起，我不是故意的，我只是…气炸了
Oh, my... I'm sorry. I didn't mean it to go so far. I was just so... So angry.
来，休息一下吧
Here, just... Let's just rest a bit.
- 我很好 - 不
- I'm all right. - No.
你不好，你累坏了
No, you're not all right. You're exhausted.
都是咕鲁害的
It's that Gollum.
这地方有鬼
It's this place.
你戴的魔戒太沉重了
It's that thing around your neck.
我可以帮忙
I could help a bit.
我可以替你戴一下
I could carry it for a while.
我替你戴一阵子
Carry it for a while.
我可以替你戴一下
I could carry it... I could carry it.
减轻你的负担
Share the load... Share the load... the load... the load.
走开
Get away!
我并不想要它
I don't want to keep it.
我只想帮忙
I just want to help.
瞧、瞧
See? See?
他想把它占为己有
He wants it for himself.
给我闭嘴
Shut up, you!
快滚，给我走吧
Go away! Get out of here!
不，山姆
No, Sam.
你才该走
It's you.
很抱歉，山姆
I'm sorry, Sam.
他是个骗子
But he's a liar.
他在挑拨我们的成情
He's poisoned you against me.
你再也帮不了我
You can't help me anymore.
这不是你的真心话
You don't mean that.
回家吧
Go home.
法拉墨！
Faramir!
你父亲完全失去理智
Your father's will has turned to madness.
不要白白去送死
Do not throw away your life so rashly.
我必须誓死效忠刚铎
Where does my allegiance lie if not here?
这是努曼诺尔人的圣城
This is the city of the Men of Numenor.
为了捍卫这座美丽的圣城，它辉煌的过去和智慧
I will gladly give my life to defend her beauty...
我很乐意牺牲我的性命
her memory, her wisdom.
你父亲很爱你，法拉墨
Your father loves you, Faramir.
他最后会明白的
He will remember it before the end.
你会唱歌吗，小哈比人？
Can you sing, Master Hobbit?
这个嘛
Well...
会啊
yes.
我的同胞觉得我唱得不错
At least, well enough for my own people.
不过我们唱的歌谣都很粗俗
But we have no songs for great halls...
不能登大雅之堂
and evil times.
为什么不能登大雅之堂？
And why should your songs be unfit for my halls?
来吧，唱一首来听听
Come, sing me a song.
家园在后方
Home is behind
世界在前方
The world ahead
路途多遥远、千辛又万苦
And there are many paths to tread
穿过幽暗阴影
Through shadow
迎向黑夜边缘
To the edge of night
直到夜空繁星闪烁
Until the stars are all alight
迷雾和阴影
Mist and shadow
乌云和黑暗
Cloud and shade
全都消失
All shall fade
All shall
消散一空
Fade
前进！前进！
March! March!
国王来了
Make way for the king.
让开
Make way.
国王来了
The king is here.
王上
My lord.
吾王万岁
Hail to you, sire.
葛林伯，有多少人马？
Grimbold, how many?
我从西谷带来五百人
I bring 500 men from the Westfold, my lord.
沼境来了三百人，希优顿王
We have 300 more from Fenmarch, Theoden King.
- 雪界河来了多少骑士？ - 个也没有，王上
- Where are the riders from Snowborn? - None have come, my lord.
六千名长矛手
Six thousand spears.
比我预期的少一半
Less than half of what I'd hoped for.
六千人不能突破魔多大军防线
Six thousand will not be enough to break the lines of Mordor.
会有更多人马来到
More will come.
时间拖久了刚铎就会沦陷
Every hour lost hastens Gondor's defeat.
只能等到天亮，然后就要出发
We have till dawn, then we must ride.
战，马焦躁不安
The horses are restless...
战士却寂静无声
and the men are quiet.
他们紧张得说不出话来
They grow nervous in the shadow of the mountain.
那条路…
That road there...
…通往哪里？
where does that lead?
那里是丁祸，黑暗之门
It is the road to the Dimholt, the door under the mountain.
没有人进去能活着出来
None who venture there ever return.
那是亡灵之山
That mountain is evil.
亚拉冈
Aragorn.
咱们去找吃的
Let's find some food.
好了
There.
你也是洛汗骠骑了
A true esquire of Rohan.
我也要打仗
I'm ready.
对不起
Sorry.
这把剑并不锐利
It isn't all that dangerous.
它其实挺钝的
It's not even sharp.
那可不行，用钝剑可杀不了半兽人
Well, that's no good. You won't kill many Orcs with a blunt blade.
来吧
Come on.
去找铁匠磨剑，去吧
To the smithy. Go!
你不该怂恿他
You should not encourage him.
你不该对他没信心
You should not doubt him.
他很有勇气，只是个子太小
I do not doubt his heart, only the reach of his arm.
梅里为什么不能上战场？
Why should Merry be left behind?
他跟你一样有参战的理由
He has as much cause to go to war as you.
他为什么就不能为他所爱的人奋战？
Why can he not fight for those he loves?
你对战争的了解跟那个哈比人一样少
You know as little of war as that Hobbit.
当他心中充满恐惧
When the fear takes him...
当他看到士兵在战场上全身血淋淋地惨叫
and the blood and the screams and the horror of battle take hold...
你认为他还会奋勇作战吗？
do you think he would stand and fight?
他一定会逃之天夭
He would flee.
他这么做并没有错
And he would be right to do so.
人类是逼不得已才会作战
War is the province of Men, Eowyn.
我选择了凡人的生命
I choose a mortal life.
我真希望能见到他…
I wish I could've seen him...
…最后一面
one last time.
大人
Sir?
希优顿王找你
King Theoden awaits you, my lord.
我先走了
I take my leave.
爱隆王
My lord Elrond.
我是为了挚爱的女儿而来
I come on behalf of one whom I love.
亚玟就快死了
Arwen is dying.
她无法抵抗魔多的邪恶力量
She will not long survive the evil that now spreads from Mordor.
暮星的光芒越来越微弱
The light of the Evenstar is failing.
索伦的力量日益强大，她就逐渐失去生命力
As Sauron's power grows, her strength wanes.
亚玟的生命和魔戒的命运息息相关
Arwen's life is now tied to the fate of the Ring.
魔影即将笼罩我们
The Shadow is upon us, Aragorn.
世界末日即将来临
The end has come.
这将是魔王的末日，不是人类的终结
It will not be our end, but his.
你们绝对无法获得胜利
You ride to war, but not to victory.
索伦的邪恶大军正向米那斯提力斯前进
Sauron's armies march on Minas Tirith, this you know.
他另外又派一支军队从河面展开攻击
But in secret he sends another force which will attack from the river.
他派昂巴海盗船从南方进攻
A fleet of Corsair ships sails from the south.
两天后就会攻到
They'll be in the city in two days.
你们寡不敌众
You're outnumbered, Aragorn.
你们需要搬更多救兵
You need more men.
没有救兵可搬了
There are none.
亡灵之山住了一些人
There are those who dwell in the mountain.
他们是杀人凶手
Murderers...
叛徒
traitors.
你要我找他们帮忙？
You would call upon them to fight?
他们什么都不相信
They believe in nothing.
也不听任何人的命令
They answer to no one.
他们会听刚铎人皇的命令
They will answer to the king of Gondor.
安都瑞尔，西方之炎用纳希尔圣剑碎月重铸而成
Anduril, the Flame of the West, forged from the shards of Narsil.
索伦绝对不会忘记伊兰迪尔圣剑
Sauron will not have forgotten the Sword of Elendil.
曾经破碎的圣剑将再度回到米那斯提力斯
The blade that was broken shall return to Minas Tirith.
能驾驭这把圣剑的人
The man who can wield the power of this sword...
将召集史上最强大的军队
can summon to him an army more deadly than any that walks this earth.
把游侠的身份放下
Put aside the Ranger.
成为你命中注定该当的人皇
Become who you were born to be.
往丁祸走上亡者之道
Take the Dimholt road.
我给人类希望
I give hope to Men.
我不是为了自己
I keep none for myself.
你为什么要走？
Why are you doing this?
大战即将在西方展开，你不能临阵脱逃
The war lies to the east. You cannot leave on the eve of battle.
你不能抛弃这些弟兄
You cannot abandon the men.
伊欧玟
Eowyn...
我们需要你
We need you here.
你为什么跟来？
Why have you come?
难道你不知道吗？
Do you not know?
你爱的只是一个理想、一个幻影
It is but a shadow and a thought that you love.
我不能回报你的爱
I cannot give you what you seek.
我第一次看到你，就希望你得到幸福
I have wished you joy since first I saw you.
你想去哪儿？
Just where do you think you're off to?
这次不行
Not this time.
这次你要留下来，金雳
This time you must stay, Gimli.
你还不知道矮人族最固执吗？
Have you learned nothing of the stubbornness of Dwarves?
你就认了吧，我们要跟你去
You might as well accept it. We're going with you, laddie.
- 么回事？ - 他要去哪儿？
- What's happening? - Where is he going?
他要去哪儿？
Where's he going?
我不明白
I don't understand.
亚拉冈大人
Lord Aragorn!
他为什么在大战前夕离开？
Why does he leave on the eve of battle?
因为他觉得没有希望
He leaves because there is no hope.
因为他非走不可
He leaves because he must.
我们势单力薄
Too few have come.
不可能击败魔多大军
We cannot defeat the armies of Mordor.
没错
No...
是不可能
we cannot.
但是我们还是要誓死奋战
But we will meet them in battle nonetheless.
我留下了指示
I have left instruction.
我死后人民要听你的命令
The people are to follow your rule in my stead.
坐上我在金殿的王位
Take up my seat in the Golden Hall.
如果我们不幸落败
Long may you defend Edoras...
你要全力捍卫伊多拉斯
if the battle goes ill.
你还要我尽什么职责？
What other duty would you have me do, my lord?
职责？
Duty?
没有了
No.
我只希望你能重展笑容
I would have you smile again...
别再为死去的人难过
not grieve for those whose time has come.
你要率领洛汗人民重建家园
You shall live to see these days renewed...
永远不再悲伤
and no more despair.
什么人会住在这种鬼地方？
What kind of army would linger in such a place?
受到诅咒的人
One that is cursed.
很久以前亡灵之山的人
Long ago, the Men of the Mountains swore an oath...
向刚铎最后一位人皇宣誓
to the last king of Gondor...
只要他一声令下
to come to his aid...
就会前来奋战
to fight.
但是当那一刻来临
But when the time came...
刚铎的战况危急
when Gondor's need was dire...
他们却仓惶逃亡
they fled...
消失在亡灵之山的阴影中
vanishing into the darkness of the mountain.
于是埃西铎诅咒他们
And so Isildur cursed them...
在实现誓言之前，他们将永远不得安息
never to rest until they had fulfilled their pledge.
谁能把他们从灰色的阴影中叫出来？
Who shall call them from the grey twilight?
被遗忘的人
The forgotten people.
他们誓言效忠人皇的继承人
The heir of him to whom the oath they swore.
他将从北方而来
From the north shall he come.
他对他们有所要求
Need shall drive him.
他将穿过黑暗之门，踏上亡者之道
He shall pass the door to the Paths of the Dead.
我全身的血液都结冰了
The very warmth of my blood seems stolen away.
黑暗之门被封住
The way is shut.
这是亡者打造的门
It was made by those who are dead.
由他们负责掌管
And the Dead keep it.
路被封住了
The way is shut.
布理哥
Brego!
我不怕死
I do not fear death.
从来没听过有这种事
Well, this is a thing unheard-of.
连精灵都肯进入地底，矮人却不敢？
An Elf will go underground where a Dwarf dare not?
真是的
Oh.
我一定会被笑死了
Oh, I'd never hear the end of it.
减轻负担、全速赶去
We must ride light and swift.
前面的路很长
It is a long road ahead.
人和马都要保留精力，才能在战场上全力奋战
And man and beast must reach the end with the strength to fight.
小哈比人不该上战场，梅里大爷
Little Hobbits do not belong in war, Master Meriadoc.
我的朋友都参战了
All my friends have gone to battle.
只有我留下来会很丢脸
I would be ashamed to be left behind.
到米那斯提力斯要骑三天
It is a three-day gallop to Minas Tirith.
我的骑士不能浪费力气载你
And none of my riders can bear you as a burden.
我想要参战
I want to fight.
别再说了
I will say no more.
跟我一起去
Ride with me.
王女
My lady.
整装出发
Form up! Move out!
出发吧
Ride!
前往刚铎
Ride now to Gondor!
是什么？
What is it?
你看见什么？
What do you see?
我看到人影
I see shapes of men.
还有马匹
And of horses.
在哪里？
Where?
像云朵一般的白旗
Pale banners like shreds of cloud.
高举的长矛
Spears rise...
就像严冬里的枯树，刺向薄薄的迷雾
like winter-thickets through a shroud of mist.
后面跟着一群亡者
The Dead are following.
他们受到召唤
They have been summoned.
亡者？
The Dead?
召唤？
Summoned?
我知道啦
I knew that.
我不怕
Very good.
我才不怕咧，勒苟拉斯
Very good! Legolas!
别往下看
Do not look down.
是谁闯入我的领土？
Who enters my domain?
你们要效忠的主人
One who will have your allegiance.
亡者不能容许活人过去
The Dead do not suffer the living to pass.
你要容许我过去
You will suffer me.
黑暗之门被封住了
The way is shut.
这是亡者打造的门
It was made by those who are dead.
由他们负责掌管
And the Dead keep it.
路被封住了
The way is shut.
你们非死不可
Now you must die.
我命令你实现你的誓言
I summon you to fulfill your oath.
只有刚铎人皇才能命令我
None but the king of Gondor may command me.
圣剑早就断裂
That line was broken.
圣剑经过重铸
It has been remade.
为我们作战
Fight for us...
重拾你们的尊严
and regain your honor.
你们怎么说？
What say you?
你在浪费时间，亚拉冈
You waste your time, Aragorn.
他们活着没尊严，死后更没有
They had no honor in life, they have none now in death.
我是埃西铎的子嗣
I am Isildur's heir.
只要为我作战
Fight for me...
你们的誓言就算实现了
and I will hold your oaths fulfilled.
怎么样？
What say you?
我向你们保证
You have my word!
只要为我作战，我就把你们从死国放走
Fight, and I will release you from this living death!
你们怎么说？
What say you?!
站出来，叛徒
Stand, you traitors!
快跑
Out!
勒苟拉斯
Legolas!
快跑
Run!
我们为你作战
We fight.
把城门打开，快点
Open the gate! Quick!
快点
Quick! Hurry!
法拉墨！
Faramir!
别跟我说他死了
Say not that he has fallen.
他们寡不敌众
They were outnumbered.
没有人生还
None survived.
恐惧
Fear.
全城充满恐惧
The city is rank with it.
让我们为他们消除恐惧
Let us ease their pain.
把犯人还给他们
Release the prisoners.
发射
Catapults!
我的儿子都死了
My sons are spent.
我的家族香火断绝了
My line has ended.
他还活着
He's alive!
宰相世家绝种了
The House of Stewards has failed.
大人，他需要救治
He needs medicine, my lord.
我绝子绝孙了
My line has ended!
大人
My lord!
洛汗人
Rohan...
抛弃了我们
has deserted us.
希优顿背叛了我
Theoden's betrayed me.
弃守吧
Abandon your posts!
快逃吧，快逃命吧
Flee! Flee for your lives!
准备迎敌
Prepare for battle!
快到墙边，保护城墙！
Hurry, men! To the wall! Defend the wall!
这里
Over here!
快回作战位置
Return to your posts!
把这些怪物打下地狱
Send these foul beasts into the abyss.
留在原地
Stay where you are.
我们需要更多石块
We need more rubble!
小心
Watch out!
到下一层，快点
Down to the lower levels. Quick!
动作快点
Double up, men!
勇敢抗敌，不要被恐惧打败
Hold them back! Do not give in to fear.
坚守岗位、誓死奋战
Stand to your posts! Fight!
不要瞄准敌军的攻城塔
Not at the towers!
瞄准食人妖，歼灭食人妖
Aim for the trolls! Kill the trolls!
把他们扳倒！
Bring them down!
把他们击退！
Fight them back!
皮聘
Peregrin Took!
- 快回去 - 你要我们誓死奋战
- Go back to the Citadel! - They'd called us out to fight.
哈比人不该上战场
This is no place for a Hobbit.
回去捍卫碉堡
Guard of the Citadel, indeed.
快回去，快点
Now, back, up the hill. Quickly. Quick!
你在干嘛？没用的东西
What are you doing, you useless scum?!
城门太坚固了，撞不破
The door won't give. It's too strong.
给我回去把它撞破
Get back there and smash it down.
用什么都撞不破
But nothing can breach it.
用葛龙德就可以
Grond will breach it.
把破城鎚拉过来
Bring up the wolf's head.
葛龙德！葛龙德！
Grond! Grond! Grond! Grond!
Grond! Grond! Grond!
葛龙德！葛龙德！
你们不能继续前进
You may go no further.
你们不能进入刚铎
You will not enter Gondor.
你们是什么人，胆敢拦我们的路？
Who are you to deny us passage?
勒苟拉斯，放一箭擦过掌帆手的耳边以示警告
Legolas, fire a warning shot past the bosun's ear.
瞄准一点
Mind your aim.
活该，我们警告过你们
That's it. Right. We warned you.
准备登船
Prepare to be boarded.
登船？
Boarded?
就凭你们跟哪支军队？
By you and whose army?
这支军队
This army.
进去
In there.
这是什么地方？
What is this place?
主人一定要进入隧道
Master must go inside the tunnel.
现在我来到这儿，我突然不想进去了
Now that I'm here, I don't think I want to.
这是唯一的路
It's the only way.
你不往前走…
Go in...
…就要回头
or go back.
我不能回头
I can't go back.
- 是什么味道？ - 半兽人的臭味
- What's that smell? - Orcses' filth.
半兽人有时候会来
Orcses come in here sometimes.
快点
Hurry.
这儿
This way.
史麦戈？
Smeagol?
这儿
Over here.
黏答答的，这是什么？
It's sticky. What is it?
你待会就知道
You will see.
没错
Oh, yes.
你等着瞧吧
You will see.
史麦戈？
Smeagol?
Smeagol!
史麦戈？
山姆
Sam.
至于你，佛罗多巴金斯
And you, Frodo Baggins...
我将埃兰迪尔之光送给你，这是我们最挚爱的星辰
I give you the light of Earendil, our most beloved star.
愿它在所有光亮熄灭时
May it be a light for you in dark places...
在黑暗中为你照亮光明
when all other lights go out.
[咒语] 向最亮的星星致敬
Aiya Earendil Elenion Ancalima! (Hail Earendil brightest of the Stars!)
小小的苍蝇
Naughty little fly.
他为什么哭？
Why does he cry?
你被困在网中
Caught in a web
很快就会被…
Soon you'll be...
吃掉
Eaten.
你以为你逃得了，是吗？
Got away, did it, precious?
这次不行
Not this time.
- 这次你休想逃 - 住手
- Not this time! - No!
不是我们，不是我们干的
It wasn't us. It wasn't us!
史麦戈不会伤害主人
Smeagol wouldn't hurt master.
我们答应过了
We promised.
你要相信我们
You must believe us.
都是宝贝害的
It was the precious.
是宝贝逼我们这么做
The precious made us do it.
我必须摧毁魔戒，史麦戈
I have to destroy it, Smeagol.
这是为了我们俩好
I have to destroy it for both our sakes.
不
No!
对不起，山姆
I'm so sorry, Sam.
真是对不起
I'm so sorry.
你被赋予这项任务，来自夏尔的佛罗多
This task was appointed to you, Frodo of the Shire.
如果你无法完成任务
If you do not find a way...
世界就会毁灭
no one will.
斥候回报说，米那斯提力斯被团团包围
The scouts report Minas Tirith is surrounded.
底层全都被大火吞蚀
The lower level's in flames.
敌军不断往前逼近
Everywhere, legions of the enemy advance.
来不及了
Time is against us.
准备作战
Make ready!
鼓起勇气
Take heart, Merry.
战争很快就结束
It will soon be over.
王女
My lady...
你是这么地勇敢美丽
you are fair and brave...
你的人生充满了希望
and have much to live for...
也有很多人爱你
and many who love you.
我知道要回头已经太迟了
I know it is too late to turn aside.
我知道再怎么期望也没有用
I know there is not much point now in hoping.
我真希望我是一个能成大事的洛汗骑士
If I were a knight of Rohan, capable of great deeds...
但我不是
But I'm not.
我只是一个哈比人
I'm a Hobbit.
我也知道我一个人救不了中土世界
And I know I can't save Middle-earth.
我只想帮助我的朋友
I just want to help my friends.
佛罗多
Frodo.
山姆
Sam.
皮聘
Pippin.
更重要的是我希望能再见到他们
More than anything, I wish I could see them again.
准备前进
Prepare to move out!
快点，我们要连夜赶路
Make haste. We ride through the night.
誓死奋战
To battle.
回去城门
Back to the gate!
快点
Hurry!
我是安那瑞安家族的宰相
I am steward of the House of Anarion.
我曾在这里昂首阔步
Thus have I walked.
现在我要在这里长眠
And thus now will I sleep.
刚铎已经沦陷了
Gondor is lost.
人类没有任何希望
There is no hope for Men.
这些傻瓜逃什么逃？
Why do the fools fly?
早一点死不是比较好吗？
Better to die sooner than late.
我们迟早都会死
For die we must.
迪耐瑟和法拉墨不需要坟墓
No tomb for Denethor and Faramir.
也不会永远况睡等待腐朽
No long, slow sleep of death embalmed.
我们要跟先王一样被烧成灰烬
We shall burn, like the heathen kings of old.
把燃油和木柴拿来
Bring wood and oil.
稳住
Steady.
你们是刚铎勇士
You are soldiers of Gondor.
不管有多少敌人，都要死守城门
No matter what comes through that gate, you will stand your ground.
快跑
Run!
放箭
Volley!
Fire!
放开他，臭东西
Let him go, you filth.
放开他
Let him go!
你休想动他一根汗毛
You will not touch him again.
有胆就来找我
Come on and finish it.
退后
Back!
佛罗多
Mr. Frodo.
不好了
Oh, no.
佛罗多
Frodo.
Mr. Frodo.
醒醒
Wake up.
别丢下我一个人
Don't leave me here alone.
别去我不能跟去的地方
Don't go where I can't follow.
快醒来
Wake up.
你不是睡着了
Not asleep.
你是死了
Dead.
给我回来，臭东西
You get back, you scum!
这是什么？
What's this?
看来尸罗又跑出来打猎了
Looks like old Shelob's been having a bit of fun.
她又杀了一个猎物？
Killed another one, has she?
没有
No.
这小子没死
This fellow ain't dead.
他没死？
Not dead?
她先用毒刺刺他，让他像死鱼一样动弹不得
She jabs him with her stinger, and he goes as limp as a boned fish.
然后她再慢慢享用大赛
Then she has her way with them.
这是她的独门秘方
That's how she likes to feed.
保持肉的鲜度
Fresh blood.
把他抬到高塔上
Get him to the tower!
山姆卫斯，你这个笨蛋
Samwise, you fool.
这臭小子两小时后就会活过来
This scum will be awake in a couple of hours.
到时候他就会不想活了
Then he'll wish he'd never been born.
他已经没救了
The house of his spirit crumbles.
他在发烧
He is burning.
他要燃烧
Already burning.
他还没死
He's not dead.
他没有死
He's not dead!
不
No! No!
住手
他还没有死
He's not dead!
- 永别了，帕拉丁之子皮聘 - 不！不！
- Farewell, Peregrin, son of Paladin. - No! No! No!
我解除你的职务
I release you from my service.
你想怎么死就去死吧
Go now and die in what way seems best to you.
把燃油倒上去
Pour oil on the wood!
快呀，别站在那儿
Come on, soldier! Move it!
- 快点，动作快点 - 甘道夫！
- Hurry along there! Hurry along! - Gandalf!
甘道夫呢？
Where is Gandalf?
甘道夫！
Gandalf!
彻退！
Retreat!
城门被攻陷了
The city is breached!
回到上面
Fall back! To the second level!
让妇孺彻退
Get the women and children out!
把他们带走
Get them out!
彻退
Retreat!
快呀，来吧
Come on. Come on, move.
攻进城内、赶尽杀绝
Move into the city. Kill all in your path.
杀光所有的敌人
Take them down!
战斗！奋战到底！
Fight! Fight to the last man!
为生存战斗！
Fight for your lives!
甘道夫！
Gandalf!
迪耐瑟发疯了
Denethor has lost his mind!
他要把法拉墨活活烧死
He's burning Faramir alive!
快上去，快
Up! Quickly!
回去黑暗深渊吧
Go back to the abyss.
跟你的主人一起回到等着你们的深渊吧
Fall into the nothingness that awaits you and your master.
你不知道你的死期到了吗？老家伙
Do you not know death when you see it, old man?
我要杀了你
This is my hour.
甘道夫！
Gandalf!
你失败了
You have failed.
人类世界会灭亡
The world of Men will fall.
鼓起勇气，梅里
Courage, Merry.
为我们的朋友鼓起勇气
Courage for our friends.
组成阵形，笨蛋，组成阵形！
Form ranks, you maggots. Form ranks!
长矛手在前、弓箭手在后
Pikes in front. Archers behind.
伊欧墨，率兵攻击左翼
Eomer, take your Eored down the left flank.
攻击左翼
Flank ready.
加姆林，跟着王旗向中锋进攻
Gamling, follow the king's banner down the center.
葛林伯，率领精兵攻击右翼
Grimbold, take your company right after you pass the wall.
前进吧，别害怕黑暗
Forth, and fear no darkness!
起来吧，希优顿王的骑士
Arise, arise, Riders of Theoden!
长矛向前刺、盾牌用力挡
Spears shall be shaken... Shields shall be splintered...
举剑奋战、血染大地
a sword-day, a red day...
我们要奋战到天明
and the sun rises!
不管怎样都紧跟着我，我会保护你
Whatever happens, stay with me. I'll look after you.
冲啊！
Ride now!
为了捍卫中土世界
Ride! Ride for ruin...
勇往直前
and the world's ending!
誓死奋战！
Death!
- 誓死奋战！ - 誓死奋战！
- Death! - Death!
冲啊，伊欧子嗣
For Eorlingas!
放箭
Fire!
誓死奋战！
Death!
冲啊！
Charge!
快放箭
Fire at will!
在我们身上点火
Set a fire in our flesh.
快给我住手
Stay this madness!
今天你也许可以打一场胜仗
You may triumph in the field of battle for a day...
但是当你面对从东方升起的邪恶力量
but against the power that has risen in the east...
你永远无法获得胜利
there is no victory.
不！
No!
你不能夺走我儿子
You will not take my son from me!
不！不！
No!
法拉墨
Faramir.
爱克西里昂之子迪耐瑟死了
So passes Denethor, son of Ecthelion.
把他们赶到河边
Drive them to the river!
捍卫王都
Make safe the city!
重组阵形
Re-form the line!
准备进攻，正面迎敌
Sound the charge! Take them head-on!
冲啊
Charge!
杀了他
Cut him down!
你来拉缰绳，往左拉
Take the reins. Pull him left!
往左
Left!
瞄准他们的头放箭
Aim for their heads!
把他扳倒…把他扳倒…
Bring it down! Bring it down! Bring it down!
梅里
Merry!
没想到我的生命在这儿走到了尽头
I didn't think it would end this way.
尽头？
End?
不，这不是尽头
No, the journey doesn't end here.
死亡只是另一条路
Death is just another path...
我们都要走的路
one that we all must take.
当灰色的天空放晴
The grey rain curtain of this world rolls back...
眼前一月银白透明
and all turns to silver glass.
你就会看见它
And then you see it.
什么？
What, Gandalf?
看见什么？
See what?
洁白的海岸
White shores...
死后的世界
and beyond.
在黎明的晨曦中
A far green country...
有一片辽阔的绿茵
under a swift sunrise.
哇塞
Well...
听起来不错嘛
that isn't so bad.
是啊
No.
是不错
No, it isn't.
大家围过来，围过来
Rally to me! To me!
好好享用他的肉
Feast on his flesh.
你敢碰他我就杀了你
I will kill you if you touch him.
别阻挡戒灵对他的猎物下手
Do not come between the Nazgul and his prey.
你们迟到了，混蛋海盗！
Late as usual, pirate scum!
准备大开杀戒吧
There's knife-work here needs doing.
快点，臭海盗，快滚下船！
Come on, you sea rats! Get off your ships!
再来比比看谁杀的敌人多
There's plenty for the both of us.
最猛的矮人一定赢
May the best Dwarf win.
你真蠢
You fool.
没有男人杀得了我
No man can kill me.
领死吧
Die now.
我不是男人
I am no man.
- 十五、十六 - 十七
- 15! 16! - 17!
梅里
Merry!
勒苟拉斯
Legolas!
三十三、三十四
33, 34.
那样也只能算一个
That still only counts as one!
好，来吧
Come on, then. Come on!
我认得你
I know your face...
伊欧玟
Eowyn.
我就快死了
My eyes darken.
不
No.
我会救你
I am going to save you.
你已经救了我
You already did.
伊欧玟
Eowyn...
我的伤势太重了
my body is broken.
你要让我走
You have to let me go.
我将加入列祖列宗的行列
I go to my fathers...
就算在伟大的先王身边
in whose mighty company...
我也不会感到羞愧
I shall not now feel ashamed.
伊欧玟
Eowyn.
让我们走吧
Release us.
最好不要
Bad idea.
这些死人头在危机时刻还挺有用的
Very handy in a tight spot, these lads, despite the fact they're dead.
你答应过我们
You gave us your word.
你们实现了誓言
I hold your oath fulfilled.
去吧
Go.
安息吧
Be at peace.
梅里
Merry.
不！
No!
随着一声叹息
With a sigh.
你转身而去
You turn away.
随着一阵心痛
With a deepening heart.
你已无话可说
No more words to say.
你会发现
You will find.
世界已经改变
That the world has changed
永远改变
forever.
树木从苍绿变成金黄
And the trees are now turning from green to gold.
太阳也将西况
And the sun is now fading.
希望我能抱住你
I wish I could hold you
靠近一点
closer.
梅里？
Merry!
梅里
Merry.
梅里，是我
Merry, it's me.
我是皮聘
It's Pippin.
我就知道你会找到我
I knew you'd find me.
当然
Yes.
你要撇下我不管吗？
Are you going to leave me?
不，梅里
No, Merry.
我要照顾你
I'm going to look after you.
别碰它
Hands off!
那件银衣是我的
That shiny shirt, that's mine.
我要把一切都交给伟大的邪眼
It's going to the Great Eye, along with everything else.
我才不听魔窟鼠辈的命令
I don't take orders from stinking Morgul-rats!
你敢碰它我就一剑把你刺死
You touch it, and I'll stick this blade in your gut.
那混球想杀我
The scum tried to knife me.
毙了他
Kill him!
这是为了佛罗多
That's for Frodo!
这是为了夏尔
And for the Shire!
这是为了我的老爹
And that's for my old Gaffer!
别哎哎叫了，臭小子
Stop your squealing, you dunghill rat.
我要在你身上刺个透明窟窿
I'm gonna bleed you like a stuck pig.
我先要你的命
Not if I stick you first.
山姆
Sam!
山姆，对不起
Oh, Sam, I'm so sorry.
我真是对不起你
Sorry for everything.
- 我先把你救出去 - 太迟了，一切都完了
- Let's get you out of here. - It's too late. It's over.
他们把它拿走了
They've taken it. Sam...
他们把魔戒拿走了
they took the Ring.
放心，他们并没有
Begging your pardon, but they haven't.
我以为你死了
I thought I'd lost you.
所以我就把它拿走
So I took it.
我只是保管它
Only for safekeeping.
把它给我
Give it to me.
把魔戒给我
Give me the Ring, Sam.
山姆
Sam.
把魔戒交给我
Give me the Ring.
你必须明白
You must understand.
魔戒是我的责任
The Ring is my burden.
它会毁了你
It will destroy you, Sam.
来吧，佛罗多
Come on, Mr. Frodo.
你最好找衣服穿
We best find you some clothes.
你不能光着身子去魔多
You can't go walking through Mordor in naught but your skin.
我们到了，佛罗多
We did it, Mr. Frodo.
我们终于到了魔多
We made it to Mordor.
有好多敌人
There are so many of them.
我们一定会被发现
We'll never get through unseen.
是他，邪眼
It's him, the Eye.
我们非去不可
We have to go in there, Mr. Frodo.
没别的选择
There's nothing for it.
来吧，先下了山再说
Come on. Let's just make it down the hill for starters.
我看不到佛罗多的行踪
Frodo has passed beyond my sight.
黑暗笼罩大地
The darkness is deepening.
如果魔戒被索伦夺去就完了
If Sauron had the Ring, we would know it.
这是迟早的事
It's only a matter of time.
他是吃了场败仗
He has suffered a defeat, yes but...
但是他正在魔多重新集结大军
behind the walls of Mordor, our enemy is regrouping.
让他留在那里吧
Let him stay there.
让他去死吧，我们为什么要怕他？
Let him rot! Why should we care?
因为有一万名半兽人大军会阻止佛罗多前往末日火山
Because 10,000 Orcs now stand between Frodo and Mount Doom.
我等于是让他去送死
I've sent him to his death.
不
No.
佛罗多仍有一线希望
There is still hope for Frodo.
他需要时间穿越葛哥洛斯平原
He needs time and safe passage across the plains of Gorgoroth.
- 我们能替他争取时间 - 该怎么做？
- We can give him that. - How?
把索伦的大军引出来
Draw out Sauron's armies.
让魔多变成空城
Empty his lands.
然后我们以全部兵力攻打黑门
Then we gather our full strength and march on the Black Gate.
我们的兵力不能打败敌人
We cannot achieve victory through strength of arms.
不必打败他们
Not for ourselves.
只要让索伦心无旁骛专心地对付我们
But we can give Frodo his chance if we keep Sauron's Eye fixed upon us.
佛罗多就有成功的机会
Keep him blind to all else that moves.
声东击西
A diversion.
成功机率很小
Certainty of death...
而且必死无疑
small chance of success...
咱们还在等什么？
what are we waiting for?
索伦一定会起疑心
Sauron will suspect a trap.
他不会上当
He will not take the bait.
他会上当
Oh, I think he will.
你一直在猎杀我
Long have you hunted me.
我也一直在躲着你
Long have I eluded you.
我不再躲藏
No more.
看我的伊兰迪尔圣剑
Behold the Sword of Elendil.
整座城市静悄悄的
The city has fallen silent.
太阳没有一丝暖意
There is no warmth left in the sun.
空气越来越冷
It grows so cold.
下了第一阵春雨才会这么潮湿冰冷
It's just the damp of the first spring rain.
我相信黑暗很快就会过去
I do not believe this darkness will endure.
你看，那些半兽人
Look, the Orcs...
他们走了
they're moving off.
你看吧，佛罗多
You see, Mr. Frodo...
我们终于有好运气了
some luck at last.
动作快点，懒虫
Move it, you slugs!
快点，快点
Come on! Faster!
快跟上来
Come along, you coldhearted wretched scum...
不然我就把你打到皮开肉绽
I'll whip you down to the bone, you...
快点
Come on!
我是怎么跟你们说的？
What have I told you?
行动起来！
Now move it!
起来
Get up!
快点，懒惰鬼
Come on, you slugs!
你们两个到前面去
You two are going straight to the front line!
快点，走快点
Now, move it! Go on! Fall in! Move it! Move it! Move it!
快到大门去，臭懒虫，快点
To the Gate, you slugs! Now, move it!
你不知道我们在打仗吗？
Don't you know we're at war?
停下来
Company, halt!
我要检查
Inspection!
山姆，帮我
Sam, help me.
佛罗多
Mr. Frodo!
起来，佛罗多，快起来
Stand up, Mr. Frodo. Stand up!
它好重
It's so heavy.
糟了
Oh, no.
我该怎么办？我们该怎么办？
What do I do? What do we do?
- 打我 - 什么？
- Hit me. - What?
打我，假装打架
Hit me, Sam. Start fighting.
给我滚开
Get off of me!
没有人敢惹我，你这臭东西
Nobody pushes me, you filthy maggot.
放开我
Get off of me!
别打了，别打了
Break it up! Break it up!
你不乖乖住手，我就把你开膛剖肚
Oi! I'll have your guts if you don't shut this rabble down!
走吧，山姆，快
Go, Sam. Now!
快走吧
Move along, scum!
回到队伍里
Back in the line!
臭东西
You maggots!
给我滚回去
Get back into the line, you slugs!
快点，懒惰鬼
Dig it, you slugs.
快点
Move it.
我不行了
I can't...
我撑不下去了，我承受不了魔戒的压力
I can't... I can't manage the Ring, Sam.
它…它…
It's... It's...
它真的好沉重
It's such a weight to carry.
它…
It's...
重到令人受不了
Such a weight.
我们要走那里，尽量直直走
We're going that way. Straight as we can.
不需要的东西说不必带
There's no point carrying anything we're not sure to need.
佛罗多
Mr. Frodo.
你看
Look.
上面有光亮
There is light...
好耀眼的光亮
and beauty up there...
没有阴影能盖住它
that no shadow can touch.
拿去
Take mine.
里面还有几滴水
There's a few drops left.
可是回程就没水喝了
There will be none left for the return journey.
我想我们是回不去了，佛罗多
I don't think there will be a return journey, Mr. Frodo.
佛罗多，快趴下
Frodo, get down!
快躲起来
Hide!
佛罗多
Frodo!
他们在哪里？
Where are they?
黑暗魔君快现身
Let the Lord of the Black Land come forth!
我要让他就地伏法
Let justice be done upon him!
我的主人索伦欢迎你们
My master, Sauron the Great, bids thee welcome.
你们哪一位可以代表跟我谈判？
Is there any in this rout with authority to treat with me?
我们不是来跟索伦谈判的
We do not come to treat with Sauron...
那个受诅咒的恶魔
faithless and accursed.
告诉你的主人，魔多大军必须解散
Tell your master this: The armies of Mordor must disband.
他要离开中土世界，永远不再回来
He is to depart these lands, never to return.
灰胡子老爹
Old Greybeard.
我有一些信物要给你看
I have a token I was bidden to show thee.
佛罗多
Frodo.
- 安静 - 不
- Silence. - No!
安静
Silence!
原来那个半身人对你们这么重要
The Halfling was dear to thee, I see.
他在我们手上受了很痛苦的折磨
Know that he suffered greatly at the hands of his host.
谁会料到这个小人儿能忍受这么大的痛苦？
Who would've thought one so small could endure so much pain?
他被折磨得不成人形
And he did, Gandalf.
痛苦不堪
He did.
这是谁？
And who is this?
埃西铎的子嗣？
Isildur's heir?
想要当人皇光有一把破烂的精灵宝剑还不够
It takes more to make a king than a broken Elvish blade.
我猜咱们的谈判结束了
I guess that concludes negotiations.
我不信
I do not believe it.
我不相信
I will not.
往后退
Pull back.
Pull back!
它走了
It's gone, Mr. Frodo.
那道光往北方移过去了
The light's passed on, away towards the north.
它被什么引开来
Something's drawn its gaze.
稳住，稳住
Hold your ground! Hold your ground.
刚铎和洛汗的好男儿，我的好兄弟
Sons of Gondor, of Rohan, my brothers!
我在你们眼中
I see in your eyes...
看见我心中也威受到的恐惧
the same fear that would take the heart of me.
有一天人类将失去勇气
A day may come when the courage of Men fails...
我们会众叛亲离、一败涂地
when we forsake our friends and break all bonds of fellowship.
但不是在今天
But it is not this day.
有一天邪将胜正
An hour of wolves and shattered shields...
人类的世界也会完全毁灭
when the age of Men comes crashing down.
但不是在今天
But it is not this day.
今天我们要誓死奋战
This day we fight!
为了你们在世上所珍惜的一切
By all that you hold dear on this good earth...
一定要奋战到底，西方的人类
I bid you stand, Men of the West!
我从来没想过我会跟一个精灵一起战死
Never thought I'd die fighting side by side with an Elf.
跟一个朋友一起战死呢？
What about side by side with a friend?
好
Aye.
我愿意
I could do that.
佛罗多，你还记得夏尔吗？
Do you remember the Shire, Mr. Frodo?
春天就快来到
It'll be spring soon.
果树都会开花
And the orchards will be in blossom.
鸟儿也会在榛树上筑巢
And the birds will be nesting in the hazel thicket.
人们很快就要收割大麦
And they'll be sowing the summer barley in the lower fields...
沾鲜奶油吃初摘的草莓
and eating the first of the strawberries with cream.
你记得草莓的味道吗？
Do you remember the taste of strawberries?
不记得
No, Sam.
我不记得食物的味道
I can't recall the taste of food...
也不记得流水声
nor the sound of water...
或是稻草香
nor the touch of grass.
我…
I'm...
…赤裸裸站在黑暗中
naked in the dark.
我跟邪眼之问
There's... there's nothing.
没有任何阻隔
No veil between me and the wheel of fire.
我的双眼…
I can see him...
…清楚地看到它
with my waking eyes.
那就把它毁掉吧
Then let us be rid of it...
让它永远消失
once and for all.
来吧，佛罗多
Come on, Mr. Frodo.
我不能替你背负这重担
I can't carry it for you...
但是我可以背你
but I can carry you.
来吧
Come on!
亚拉冈
Aragorn.
伊力萨王
Elessar.
为了佛罗多
For Frodo.
你看，佛罗多
Look, Mr. Frodo.
一道门
A doorway.
就快到了
We're almost there.
聪明的哈比人爬到这么高
Clever Hobbits to climb so high!
不能去那边
Mustn't go that way.
不能毁了宝贝
Mustn't hurt the precious.
你发过誓
You swore!
你对着宝贝发誓
You swore on the precious!
史麦戈发过誓
Smeagol promised!
史麦戈是骗你的
Smeagol lied.
佛罗多
Frodo!
巨鹰
Eagles.
巨鹰来帮忙了
The eagles are coming!
佛罗多
Frodo!
我在这里，山姆
I'm here, Sam.
毁了它
Destroy it!
快点，快呀
Go on! Now!
把它丢进烈焰中
Throw it in the fire!
你还在等什么？
What are you waiting for?
快放手
Just let it go!
魔戒是我的
The Ring is mine.
不
No.
不要
不！
No!
好耶
Yes!
宝贝！宝贝！
Precious! Precious!
把手伸出来
Give me your hand!
抓住我的手
Take my hand!
不！
No!
千万别放手
Don't you let go.
别放手
Don't let go.
抓住
Reach!
佛罗多！
Frodo!
它不见了
It's gone.
任务完成了
It's done.
没错，佛罗多
Yes, Mr. Frodo.
一切都结束了
It's over now.
我看得见夏尔了
I can see the Shire.
烈酒河
The Brandywine River.
袋底洞
Bag End.
甘道夫的烟火
Gandalf's fireworks.
宴会树上的灯光
The lights in the Party Tree.
小玟卡顿在跳舞
Rosie Cotton dancing.
她头上绑了丝带
She had ribbons in her hair.
如果我要娶老婆
If ever I was to marry someone...
一定要娶她
it would've been her.
一定会是她
It would've been her.
我很高兴有你在，山姆卫斯詹吉
I'm glad to be with you, Samwise Gamgee...
陪我一起走到尽头
here at the end of all things.
甘道夫？
Gandalf?
佛罗多
Frodo!
金雳
Gimli!
人皇的时代来临了
Now come the days of the king.
愿神祝福你
May they be blessed.
这一天的荣耀不是属于一个人
This day does not belong to one man...
而是属于每一个人
but to all.
让我们同心协力重建家园
Let us together rebuild this world...
一起分享太平盛世
that we may share in the days of peace.
# [精灵语] 走出大海
# Et Earello... (Out of the Great Sea...)
# [精灵语] 去往中土大陆
# Endorenna utulien. (to Middle-Earth I am come.)
# [精灵语] 我要住在这个地方
# Sinome maruvan... (In this place will I abide...)
# [精灵语] 和我的子孙
# ar Hildinyar... (and my heirs...)
# [精灵语] 直到世界末日
# tenn' Ambar-metta. (unto the ending of the world.)
[精灵语] 谢谢
Hannon le. (Thank you.)
我的朋友们
My friends...
你们不必向任何人鞠躬
you bow to no one.
故事终于告一段落
And thus it was.
中土世界第四纪元就此展开
A Fourth Age of Middle-earth began.
至于魔戒远征队
And the Fellowship of the Ring...
虽然他们的友谊永远长存
though eternally bound by friendship and love...
但是也该曲终人散
was ended.
甘道夫派我们踏上这段旅程的十三个月后
Thirteen months to the day since Gandalf sent us on our long journey...
我们终于再度看到熟悉的景象
we found ourselves looking upon a familiar sight.
我们回家了
We were home.
嗨
Hi.
小心我的南瓜
Hey, watch the pumpkin.
再来一杯，小玟
More of the same, Rosie.
晚安，各位
Good night, lads.
你该如何重拾往日的生活？
How do you pick up the threads of an old life?
你该怎么继续下去？
How do you go on...
当你在内心深处早就知道
when in your heart you begin to understand...
你已无法回头
there is no going back?
有些事情无法弥补
There are some things that time cannot mend...
有些伤痛太深沉
some hurts that go too deep...
你将永远无法复元
that have taken hold.
(历险归来: 哈比人的故事  比尔博巴金斯著)
佛罗多？
Mr. Frodo?
怎么了？
What is it?
我在风云顶上被刺这一剑，到现在已经过了四年了
It's been four years to the day since Weathertop, Sam.
伤口还是没有完全愈合
It's never really healed.
历险归来: 哈比人的故事，比尔博巴金斯著
"There and Back Again." A Hobbit's tale by Bilbo Baggins.
魔戒之王，佛罗多巴金斯著
And "The Lord of the Rings" by Frodo Baggins.
你写完了
You finished it.
还没有
Not quite.
还有一些故事没写完
There's room for a little more.
比尔博曾说他的故事终会结束
Bilbo once told me his part in this tale would end...
每个人的生命都有精采的一页
that each of us must come and go in the telling.
他的故事已经结束
Bilbo's story was now over.
比尔博即将踏上…
There would be no more journeys for him...
…最后的旅程
save one.
再告诉我，我们要去哪儿？
Tell me again, lad, where are we going?
去港口呀
To the harbor, Bilbo.
精灵赐给你最高的荣誉
The Elves have accorded you a special honor...
跟他们一起搭船离闭中土世界
a place on the last ship to leave Middle-earth.
佛罗多
Frodo...
我能再见到那只戒指吗？
any chance of seeing that old Ring of mine again?
我给你的那只戒指
The one I gave you.
对不起，叔叔
I'm sorry, Uncle.
我把它弄丢了
I'm afraid I lost it.
噢
Oh.
真可惜
Pity.
我很想再持有它最后一次
I should like to have held it one last time.
我没见过这么大的场面
Well, here's a sight I have never seen before.
精灵族的三只魔戒力量已消失
The power of the Three Rings is ended.
人类统治的时代
The time has come...
已经来临
for the dominion of Men.
大海在召唤我们回家
I Aear can ven na mar.
我想
I think I'm...
我准备好再踏上另一场冒险之旅了
quite ready for another adventure.
再会吧
Farewell...
勇敢的哈比人
my brave Hobbits.
我的任务已经完成
My work is now finished.
在这大海的岸边
Here at last, on the shores of the sea...
魔戒远征队终于解散了
comes the end of our Fellowship.
我不会叫你们不要哭
I will not say, "Do not weep"...
因为有些泪水是好的
for not all tears are an evil.
该走了，佛罗多
It is time, Frodo.
他是什么意思？
What does he mean?
我们的任务是拯救夏尔
We set out to save the Shire, Sam.
夏尔安然无恙
And it has been saved.
但我不能留下来
But not for me.
你不是说真的
You don't mean that.
你不能走
You can't leave.
最后几页是留给你的，山姆
The last pages are for you, Sam.
亲爱的山姆
My dear Sam
你不能一心两用
You cannot always be torn in two.
你必须全心全意为家庭奉献
You will have to be one and whole for many years.
你有好多事要做，有好多福可享
You have so much to enjoy and to be and to do.
你在故事中的角色将继续下去
Your part in the story will go on.
好了
Well...
我回家了
I'm back.